Guide to the Kaufman family papers, 1900-2021 MS 769
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Kaufman family papers
1900-2021
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Kaufman, Stephen M.
MS 769
0.5 Linear Feet 1 box
The collection includes certificates, correspondence, family photos, publications, a Bellaire High School commencement program, speeches, a scrapbook, an oral history, and memorabilia from the 1960 Democratic National Convention that document the activities of Stephen Kaufman, primarily, and to a lesser extent his wife, Ann, and both of their families.
Biographical / Historical
Stephen M. Kaufman was born in 1941, in Houston, Texas. Mr. Kaufman grew up in Houston and graduated from Bellaire Senior High School in 1958. After graduation, he attended Harvard College where he received a Bachelor of Arts degree in Economics, Magna Cum Laude, in 1962. His last two years at Harvard involved intense study of life insurance company taxation, which culminated in his honors thesis entitled, "The Life Insurance Company Income Tax Act of 1959." which was published in the National Tax Journal in December 1963 and March 1964. Mr. Kaufman built a long and successful career in the life insurance business.
At the time of his graduation, Kaufman received a commission as Ensign in the U.S. Navy and served aboard the destroyer USS John Hood during the Cuban Missile Crisis. He completed his tour of duty on July 1, 1964 with the rank of Lieutenant Junior Grade. He was honorably discharged from the Navy in 1972.
Stephen married Ann Poborsky in Houston on March 14, 1974. Stephen and Ann have been fixtures in the community and have been actively involved in Congregation Beth Israel, the American Jewish Committee, and the Houston Grand Opera among many other organizations. Both Stephen and Ann have been recipients of the David H. White award for recognition of their community involvement.
Scope and Contents
One box of certificates, correspondence, memorabilia, photographs, publications, a commencement program, speeches, and a scrapbook document the lives of the Stephen and Ann Kaufman's family from 1900 to 2012. Of particular interest are a personal letter to Stephen Kaufman from Vice President Lyndon Johnson and a badge and general admission pass to the 1960 Democratic National Convention. There is also an oral history interview with Stephen Kaufman available online in our institutional repository: https://scholarship.rice.edu/handle/1911/110317.
Conditions Governing Access
This material is open for research.
Stored offsite at the Library Service Center and require 24-hour notice for retrieval. Please contact the Woodson Research Center at 713-348-2586 or woodson@rice.edu for more information.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials were donated by Stephen Kaufman October 2018.
Arrangement
The materials in this collection have been arranged in eight series as follows:
Series I: Certificates; Series II: Correspondence; Series III: Memorabilia; Series IV: Photographs; Series V: Programs; Series VI: Publications; Series VII: Scrapbook; Series VIII: Speeches; Series IX: Oral History
Index Terms
Subjects
Military; Insurance; World War (1939-1945); Jews and Jewish life; Politics and government
Document Types
certificates; personal correspondence; memorabilia; programs (documents); black-and-white photographs; publications; scrapbooks; speeches; Oral histories
Subjects (Persons)
Kaufman, Stephen M.; Johnson, Lyndon B. (Lyndon Baines), 1908-1973
Subjects (Corporations)
Congregation Beth Israel (Houston, Tex.)
- Series I: Certificates, 1972-1980
  - From United Jewish Appeal for participating in Young Leadership Cabinet, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Stephen and Ann Kaufman's marriage license (copy), 1974-03 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Stephen Kaufman's "Honorable Discharge" from the U.S. Navy, 1972-10-30 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Series II: Correspondence, 1960-2007
  - Letter to Stephen Kaufman from Vice President Lyndon Johnson, 1961-09-01 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Stephen's granddaughter's family tree, 2007 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence from Stephen at Democratic National Convention, 1960-07 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Letter to Albert Kaufman from Stephen's Commanding Officer, 1961-02-10 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Series III: Memorabilia, 1960
  - Democratic National Convention, 1960-07 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Series IV: Photographs, 1900-1960
  - Stephen Kaufman's confirmation class, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Stephen Kaufman and Uncle William Salmon at Democratic National Convention, 1960-07 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Stephen Kaufman's SAR football team group photo, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Stephen and Ann Kaufman's family photographs, 1900-1953 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Series V: Programs, 1958-1964
  - Introducing Stephen Kaufman as new associate for The Warren S. Griffin Agency, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Stephen Kaufman's Bellaire Senior High School commencement, 1958-05-28 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Series VI: Publications, 1973-2012
  - Kaufman mentions in Houston Jewish community publications, 1973; 1977; 2012 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - "The Paintings of Frank Freed" (Ann Kaufman's first cousin), 1996 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - "Opera Cues" (Houston Grand Opera), 2012 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Series VII: Scrapbook, 1934-2004
  - Stephen Kaufman's Scrapbook, 1934-1955; 1960; 2003-2004 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Series VIII: Speeches, 1987-2006
  - "Reflections on a Career in the Life Insurance Business," HAIFA luncheon, 2006-01-12 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Stephen Kaufman's acceptance speech - David H. White award, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Stephen Kaufman's presentation of David H. White award to Ann Kaufman, 1995-05-11 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Stephen Kaufman at dedication of Jean and Albert Kaufman Building, Congregation Beth Israel, 1987-10-11 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Series IX: Oral History, 2021
  - Stephen Kaufman oral history interview and transcript, 2021-02-08